I'm going to talk to you about optimism --
سأحدثكم عن التفاؤل -
or more precisely, the optimism bias.
أو بشكل أدق، الميل للتفاؤل .
It's a cognitive illusion
إنه عبارة عن وهم ذهني
that we've been studying in my lab for the past few years,
عكفنا على دراسته في مختبري في السنوات القليلة الماضية،
and 80 percent of us have it.
و يملكه 80% منا.
It's our tendency to overestimate
إنه ميلنا للإفراط في تقدير
our likelihood of experiencing good events in our lives
إمكانية المرور بظروف حسنة في حياتنا
and underestimate our likelihood of experiencing bad events.
وللتقليل من إمكانية المرور بظروف سيئة.
So we underestimate our likelihood of suffering from cancer,
فنحن نقلل تقديرنا لإمكانية إصابتنا بالسرطان،
being in a car accident.
أو الوقوع في حادث مروري.
We overestimate our longevity, our career prospects.
و نفرط في توقع عمرطويل، و مستقبل مهني زاهر.
In short, we're more optimistic than realistic,
باختصار، نحن متفائلون أكثر مما نحن واقعيون،
but we are oblivious to the fact.
ولكننا غافلون عن الحقيقة.
Take marriage for example.
خذ الزواج على سبيل المثال.
In the Western world, divorce rates are about 40 percent.
في العالم الغربي، تصل نسبة الطلاق إلى 40 في المائة تقريباً.
That means that out of five married couples,
هذا يعني أنه من كل خمس أزواج،
two will end up splitting their assets.
سينتهي المطاف بإثنين منهم إلى اقتسام أملاكهما.
But when you ask newlyweds about their own likelihood of divorce,
ولكن عندما تسأل الأزواج حديثي العهد عن إمكانية طلاقهم هم شخصيا
they estimate it at zero percent.
فإنهم يقدرونها بـ 0 بالمائة.
And even divorce lawyers, who should really know better,
حتى المحامون المختصون في الطلاق، و المفترض أن يكونوا أكثر اطلاعا،
hugely underestimate their own likelihood of divorce.
يقللون بشكل كبير من إمكانية طلاقهم شخصيا .
So it turns out that optimists are not less likely to divorce,
إذاً، يتبين أنّ إمكانية طلاق المتفائليين ليست أقل،
but they are more likely to remarry.
ولكن إمكانية زواجهم مجددا أكبر.
In the words of Samuel Johnson,
كما قال سامويل جونسون،
"Remarriage is the triumph of hope over experience."
"الزواج مجددا هو انتصار الأمل على التجربة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So if we're married, we're more likely to have kids.
إذاً، إذا كنا متزوجين فمن المرجح أن يكون لدينا أطفال.
And we all think our kids will be especially talented.
وكلنا نعتقد بأن أطفالنا سيكونون موهوبين بشكل خاص.
This, by the way, is my two-year-old nephew, Guy.
هذا، على فكرة، هو ابن أخي "جاي" ذو السنتين.
And I just want to make it absolutely clear
وأريد أن أوضّح بشكل تام
that he's a really bad example of the optimism bias,
أنهُ مثال سيّء تماماً عن الميل للتفائل،
because he is in fact uniquely talented.
لأنه في الحقيقة موهوب بشكل فريد من نوعه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm not alone.
وأنا لست الوحيدة.
Out of four British people, three said
من كل أربعة أشخاص بريطانيين، ثلاثة قالوا
that they were optimistic about the future of their own families.
بأنهم متفائلون بمستقبل عائلاتهم.
That's 75 percent.
أي 75% منهم.
But only 30 percent said
ولكن 30% منهم فقط قالوا
that they thought families in general
بأنهم يعتقدون بشكل عام أنّ العائلات
are doing better than a few generations ago.
الآن بوضع أفضل منه مقارنة ببضع أجيال مضت.
And this is a really important point,
وهذه نقطة مهمة جداً،
because we're optimistic about ourselves,
لأننا متفائلون بخصوص أنفسنا،
we're optimistic about our kids,
متفائلون بخصوص أطفالنا،
we're optimistic about our families,
متفائلون بخصوص عائلاتنا،
but we're not so optimistic about the guy sitting next to us,
ولكننا لسنا متفائلين بنفس الشكل بخصوص الشخص الجالس بجوارنا،
and we're somewhat pessimistic
ومتشائمون بعض الشيء
about the fate of our fellow citizens and the fate of our country.
بخصوص مصير مواطنينا ومصير بلدنا.
But private optimism about our own personal future
لكن التفاؤل الفردي بخصوص مستقبلنا الخاص
remains persistent.
يبقى راسخا.
And it doesn't mean that we think things will magically turn out okay,
و هذا لا يعني أننا نعتقد بأن الأمور ستتحسن بطريقة سحرية،
but rather that we have the unique ability to make it so.
بل نعتقد بأن لدينا القدرة الفريدة على جعلها كذلك.
Now I'm a scientist, I do experiments.
أنا باحثة، وأقوم بتجارب.
So to show you what I mean,
ولأوضّح لكم ما أقصد،
I'm going to do an experiment here with you.
سأقوم بعمل تجربة هنا معكم .
So I'm going to give you a list of abilities and characteristics,
سأعطيكم قائمة تحتوي على قدراتٍ و ِصفات،
and I want you to think for each of these abilities
وأريدكم أن تفكروا، بخصوص كل واحدة من هذه القدرات،
where you stand relative to the rest of the population.
أين تتموضعون بالنسبة لبقية السكان.
The first one is getting along well with others.
أول واحدة هي المقدرة على الألفة (التفاهم مع الأخرين)
Who here believes they're at the bottom 25 percent?
من منكم هنا يعتقد بأنه من بين الـ 25% الأقل حظاً؟
Okay, that's about 10 people out of 1,500.
حسناً، هذا حوالي 10 أشخاص من بين 1500.
Who believes they're at the top 25 percent?
من يعتقد بأنه من بين الـ 25% الأعلى حظاً؟
That's most of us here.
ذلك معظمنا هنا.
Okay, now do the same for your driving ability.
حسناً، الآن افعلوا الأمر نفسه بالنسبة للقدرة على قيادة السيارة.
How interesting are you?
ما مقدار أهميتك؟
How attractive are you?
و ما قدر جاذبيتك؟
How honest are you?
وكم أنت شريف الخُلُق؟
And finally, how modest are you?
وأخيراً، ما قدر تواضعك؟
So most of us put ourselves above average
إذاً، معظمنا يصنّف نفسه فوق المعدّل
on most of these abilities.
بالنسبة لمعظم هذه القدرات.
Now this is statistically impossible.
حسناً، هذا مستحيل إحصائياً .
We can't all be better than everyone else.
لا يمكن أن يكون جميعنا أفضل من كل الأفراد الأخرين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if we believe we're better than the other guy,
ولكن إذا اعتقد كلٌّ منا أنه أفضل من الشخص الآخر،
well that means that we're more likely to get that promotion, to remain married,
فذلك يعني أنه من المرجّح أن نحصل على ترقية، أن نبقى متزوجين،
because we're more social, more interesting.
لأننا اجتماعيون أكثر، و أكثر أهمية.
And it's a global phenomenon.
وتلك ظاهرة عالمية.
The optimism bias has been observed
الميل للتفائل لوحظ
in many different countries --
في عدة دول مختلفة -
in Western cultures, in non-Western cultures,
في ثقافات غربية وغير غربية،
in females and males,
في الإناث والذكور،
in kids, in the elderly.
في الصغار والكبار.
It's quite widespread.
إنه جد منتشر.
But the question is, is it good for us?
ولكن السؤال الذي يُطرح، هل هو في صالحنا؟
So some people say no.
بعض الناس يقولون لا.
Some people say the secret to happiness
البعض يقول سر السعادة
is low expectations.
هو التوقعات المتواضعة.
I think the logic goes something like this:
أعتقد أن المنطق في ذلك هو كالآتي:
If we don't expect greatness,
إذا لم نتوقع العظمة،
if we don't expect to find love and be healthy and successful,
إذا لم نتوقع أن نجد الحب و نكون بصحة جيدة و ناجحيين،
well we're not going to be disappointed when these things don't happen.
لن يخيب أملنا عندما لا تحدث هذه الأشباء.
And if we're not disappointed when good things don't happen,
وإذا لم نصب بخيبة أمل لعدم حدوث الخير،
and we're pleasantly surprised when they do,
ونتفاجأ فنسرّ بحدوثها،
we will be happy.
عندها سنكون سعداء.
So it's a very good theory,
حسناً، إنها نظرية جيدة جداً،
but it turns out to be wrong for three reasons.
ولكن يتبين أنها خاطئة لثلاث أسباب.
Number one: Whatever happens, whether you succeed or you fail,
أولاً: بغض النظر عمّا يحصل ، سواء نجحت أم أخفقت،
people with high expectations always feel better.
أصحاب التوقعات العالية هم أكثر ارتياحاً.
Because how we feel when we get dumped or win employee of the month
لأن ما نشعر به عندما يتخلّى عنا أحبتنا أو عندما نفوز بشهادة "أحسن موظف في الشهر"
depends on how we interpret that event.
يعتمد على كيفية تفسيرنا لذلك الحدث.
The psychologists Margaret Marshall and John Brown
عالما النفس مارجريت مارشال و جون براون
studied students with high and low expectations.
درسا طُلابا ذوي توقعات عالية و منخفضة.
And they found that when people with high expectations succeed,
فوجدا أنه عندما ينجح أصحاب التوقعات العالية،
they attribute that success to their own traits.
فإنهم بنسبون ذلك النجاح إلى صفاتهم الفردية.
"I'm a genius, therefore I got an A,
أنا عبقري، لذلك حصلت على درجة التميّز،
therefore I'll get an A again and again in the future."
و لذلك سأحصل عليها مرات ومرات أخرى مستقبلاً."
When they failed, it wasn't because they were dumb,
عندما أخفقوا، لم يكن ذلك لأنهم كانوا أغبياء،
but because the exam just happened to be unfair.
بل فقط لأن الاختبار كان غير عادلاً.
Next time they will do better.
في المرة القادمة سيكون أداؤهم أفضل.
People with low expectations do the opposite.
أصحاب التوقعات المنخفضة يفعلون العكس.
So when they failed it was because they were dumb,
فلمّا أخفقوا كان ذلك بسبب غبائهم
and when they succeeded
وعندما نجحوا
it was because the exam just happened to be really easy.
كان ذلك لأنه تصادف وكان الاختبار سهلاً.
Next time reality would catch up with them.
في المرة القادمة سيستدركهم الواقع.
So they felt worse.
ولذلك يستاء شعورهم.
Number two: Regardless of the outcome,
ثانياً، بغض النظر عن المآل،
the pure act of anticipation makes us happy.
مجرد الترقّب يجعلنا سعداء.
The behavioral economist George Lowenstein
عالم السلوك الاقتصادي جورج لوفينستين
asked students in his university
سأل طلابا في جامعته
to imagine getting a passionate kiss from a celebrity, any celebrity.
أن يتخيلوا الحصول على قبلة حارة من أحد المشاهير، أيّا كان.
Then he said, "How much are you willing to pay
وبعد ذلك سألهم : "كم من المال أنتم مستعدون أن تدفعوا
to get a kiss from a celebrity
لتحصلوا على قبلة من أحد المشاهير
if the kiss was delivered immediately,
لو أنه قبّلكم حالاً؟
in three hours, in 24 hours, in three days,
بعد 3 ساعات؟ بعد 24 ساعة؟ بعد ثلاثة أيام؟
in one year, in 10 years?
بعد سنة؟ وبعد 10 سنين؟
He found that the students were willing to pay the most
وجد أنّ الطلاب كانوا مستعدين لدفع أكبر قدر من المال
not to get a kiss immediately,
لا للحصول على القبلة حالاً،
but to get a kiss in three days.
لكن للحصول عليها بعد ثلاثة أيام.
They were willing to pay extra in order to wait.
كانوا على استعدادٍ لدفع المزيد حتى ينتظروا.
Now they weren't willing to wait a year or 10 years;
حسناً، لم يكونوا مستعدين للانتظار لسنة أو لعشر سنوات.
no one wants an aging celebrity.
لا أحد يرغب في مشهورٍ في شيخوخته.
But three days seemed to be the optimum amount.
ولكن بدا أن ثلاثة أيام هي القدر الأمثل.
So why is that?
فلماذا الأمورهي هكذا؟
Well if you get the kiss now, it's over and done with.
إذا حصلت على القبلة الآن، فالأمر انتهى و فُرغ منه.
But if you get the kiss in three days,
أمّا إن كنت ستحصل عليها بعد ثلاثة أيام،
well that's three days of jittery anticipation, the thrill of the wait.
فتلك ثلاثة أيام من الإستباق المتوتر، ومن نشوة الإنتظار.
The students wanted that time
أراد الطلاب ذلك الوقت
to imagine where is it going to happen,
لكي يتخيلوا أين ستحصل
how is it going to happen.
وكيف ستحصل.
Anticipation made them happy.
جعلهم الاستباق سعداء.
This is, by the way, why people prefer Friday to Sunday.
وذلك، على فكرة، سبب تفضيل الناس ليوم الجمعة على الأحد.
It's a really curious fact,
هذا فعلا واقع غريب،
because Friday is a day of work and Sunday is a day of pleasure,
لأن الجمعة يوم عمل و الأحد يوم استمتاع،
so you'd assume that people will prefer Sunday,
فلأول وهلة يُفترَض أنّ الناس يفضّلون يوم الأحد،
but they don't.
ولكنهم لا يفضلونه.
It's not because they really, really like being in the office
لا لإنهم فعلا يعشقون التواجد بالمكتب
and they can't stand strolling in the park
و لا يطيقون التجوال في المتنزهات
or having a lazy brunch.
أو تتاول وجبة فطور متأخرة بتكاسل.
We know that, because when you ask people
نعلم هذا لأنه عندما تسأل الناس
about their ultimate favorite day of the week,
عن يومهم المفضل في الأسبوع دون منازع،
surprise, surprise, Saturday comes in at first,
مفاجئة ! يحل يوم السبت أولاً،
then Friday, then Sunday.
ثم يوم الجمعة و يليه يوم الأحد.
People prefer Friday
الناس يفضلون يوم الجمعة
because Friday brings with it the anticipation of the weekend ahead,
لأن يوم الجمعة يجلب معه استباقا لنهاية الأسبوع المقبل
all the plans that you have.
وما حوى من ترتيبات.
On Sunday, the only thing you can look forward to
في يوم الأحد، الأمر الوحيد الذي تتطلع إليه
is the work week.
هو أسبوع من العمل.
So optimists are people who expect more kisses in their future,
فالمتفائلون هم أناس يترقبون قبلات أكثر بالمستقبل،
more strolls in the park.
وجولات أكثر في المتنزهات.
And that anticipation enhances their wellbeing.
ويدعم ذاك الاستباق راحتهم النفسية.
In fact, without the optimism bias,
في الحقيقة، من دون الميل للتفاؤل،
we would all be slightly depressed.
قد يعترينا شيئ من الإحباط.
People with mild depression,
الأشخاص الذين لديهم إحباط معتدل،
they don't have a bias when they look into the future.
ليس لديهم أيّ ميل عندما ينظرون إلي المستقبل.
They're actually more realistic than healthy individuals.
هم أشخاص واقعيون أكثر منهم ذوي سلوك صحّي.
But individuals with severe depression,
لكن الأشخاص الذين لديهم إحباط شديد،
they have a pessimistic bias.
يملكون ميلاً للتشاؤم.
So they tend to expect the future
فهم يميلون لتوقع مستقبلٍ
to be worse than it ends up being.
أسوء مما سيحصل في نهاية المطاف.
So optimism changes subjective reality.
فالتشاؤم يغيّر الواقع الذاتي.
The way we expect the world to be changes the way we see it.
الطريقة التي نتوقع أن يكون عليها العالم تُغيّر الطريقة التي نراه بها.
But it also changes objective reality.
لكنها تغيّر الواقع الموضوعي.
It acts as a self-fulfilling prophecy.
تعمل و كأنها رؤيا قد تحققت فعلاً.
And that is the third reason
و هذا هو السبب الثالث
why lowering your expectations will not make you happy.
الذي من أجله لا يجعلك تقليل التوقعات سعيداً.
Controlled experiments have shown
بيّنت التجارب المتحكّم فيها
that optimism is not only related to success,
بأن التفاؤل لا يرتبط فقط بالنجاح،
it leads to success.
بل يقود إليه.
Optimism leads to success in academia and sports and politics.
يقود التفاؤل نحو النجاح في الميدان الأكاديمي و الرياضي و السياسي.
And maybe the most surprising benefit of optimism is health.
وقد تكون الفائدة الأكثر مفاجئة للنجاح هي الصحة.
If we expect the future to be bright,
إذا توقعنا أن يكون المستقبل برّاقا،
stress and anxiety are reduced.
يقّل التوتر والقلق.
So all in all, optimism has lots of benefits.
و مجملاً، في التفاؤل كثيرٌ من الفوائد.
But the question that was really confusing to me was,
لكن السؤال الذي جعلني فعلا في حيرة من أمري،
how do we maintain optimism in the face of reality?
هو كيف نبقي على التفاؤل في مواجهة الواقع؟
As an neuroscientist, this was especially confusing,
كمختصة في علم الأعصاب، كان هذا جدّ مربك،
because according to all the theories out there,
لأنه وبحسب كل النظريات الشائعة،
when your expectations are not met, you should alter them.
إذا لم تتحقق توقعاتك، فعليك بتغييرها.
But this is not what we find.
لكن ليس هذا ما نجد.
We asked people to come into our lab
طلبنا من أشخاص الحضور إلى مخبرنا
in order to try and figure out what was going on.
كي نحاول أن نتعرف على ما يجري.
We asked them to estimate their likelihood
طلبنا منهم أن يقدروا إمكانية
of experiencing different terrible events in their lives.
خوضهم مختلف الأحداث المؤلمة في حياتهم.
So, for example, what is your likelihood of suffering from cancer?
على سبيل المثال، "ما هي إمكانية إصابتكم بمرض السرطان؟"
And then we told them the average likelihood
وبعدها أخبرناهم بالإمكانية المتوسطة
of someone like them to suffer these misfortunes.
بأن تحل هذه المصائب بشخصٍ مثلِهم
So cancer, for example, is about 30 percent.
فمثلاً، حوالي 30% لمرض السرطان.
And then we asked them again,
ثم سألناهم مجدّدًا،
"How likely are you to suffer from cancer?"
"ما هي إمكانية إصابتكم بمرض السرطان؟"
What we wanted to know was
ما أردنا معرفته
whether people will take the information that we gave them
هو ما إذا كان الناس سيأخذون في الاعتبار المعلومة التي أعطيناهم
to change their beliefs.
ليغيروا معتقداتهم.
And indeed they did --
و فعلاً قاموا بذلك -
but mostly when the information we gave them
لكن غالباً لمّا كانت المعلومة التي أعطايناهم
was better than what they expected.
أحسن ممّا توقعوا.
So for example,
فمثلاً
if someone said, "My likelihood of suffering from cancer
إذا قال أحدهم: "إمكانية إصابتي بالسرطان
is about 50 percent,"
حوالي 50 %"،
and we said, "Hey, good news.
و قلنا له: "إسمع! خبرٌ سار..
The average likelihood is only 30 percent,"
متوسط الإمكانية هو فقط 30%"،
the next time around they would say,
في الكرّة التالية سيقول:
"Well maybe my likelihood is about 35 percent."
"حسنًا، إمكانية إصابتي هي حوالي 35%".
So they learned quickly and efficiently.
فقد تعلّموا بسرعة و فعالية.
But if someone started off saying,
لكن إذا قال أحدهم أول ما قال،
"My average likelihood of suffering from cancer is about 10 percent,"
"إمكانية إصابتي بالسرطان هي حوالي 10%"،
and we said, "Hey, bad news.
و قلنا: "إسمع! خبرً غير سار.
The average likelihood is about 30 percent,"
متوسط (تلك) الإمكانية هو فقط 30%"
the next time around they would say,
في الكرة التالية سيقول:
"Yep. Still think it's about 11 percent."
" آه. لا أزال أظنها 11%"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So it's not that they didn't learn at all -- they did --
فالأمر ليس كونهم لم يتعلموا بتاتًا - قاموا بذلك -
but much, much less than when we gave them
لكن بدرجة أقلّ، أقلّ بكثير من لمّا أعطيناهم
positive information about the future.
معلومة إيجابية عن المستقبل.
And it's not that they didn't remember the numbers that we gave them;
و ليس الأمر كونهم لم يتذكروا الأرقام التي أعطيناهم،
everyone remembers that the average likelihood of cancer
الكل يتذكر أنّ متوسط إمكانية الإصابة بالسرطان
is about 30 percent
هو حوالي 30%
and the average likelihood of divorce is about 40 percent.
متوسط إمكانية الطلاق هو 40%.
But they didn't think that those numbers were related to them.
لكنهم لم يعتقدوا أن تعنيهم تلك الأرقام.
What this means is that warning signs such as these
ما يعنيه ذلك أن إشاراتٍ محذّرةٍ كهذه
may only have limited impact.
قد يكون أثرها جد محدود.
Yes, smoking kills, but mostly it kills the other guy.
نعم، التدخين يؤدي إلى الموت، و لكنه يقتل شخصًا آخر على الأرجح.
What I wanted to know was
ما أردت معرفته هو
what was going on inside the human brain
ما كان يدور بالذهن البشري
that prevented us from taking these warning signs personally.
ويمنعه من الأخذ بهذه الإشارات المحذرة شخصيّاً.
But at the same time,
لكن في نفس الوقت،
when we hear that the housing market is hopeful,
عندما نسمع بأنّ التوقعات بخصوص سوق العقارجيدة،
we think, "Oh, my house is definitely going to double in price."
نخمّن : "حسناً، سيتضاعف سعر منزلي بالتأكيد".
To try and figure that out,
من أجل استبيان ذلك،
I asked the participants in the experiment
طلبت من المشاركين في التجربة
to lie in a brain imaging scanner.
أن يستلقوا داخل ماسح مصور للدماغ.
It looks like this.
إنه يشبه هذا.
And using a method called functional MRI,
و بالاعتماد على طريقة تسمى بـ"التصوير الوظيفي عبر الرنين المغناطيسي"
we were able to identify regions in the brain
تمكنّا من التعرف على المناطق داخل الدماغ
that were responding to positive information.
التي كانت تستجيب للمعلومات الإيجابية.
One of these regions is called the left inferior frontal gyrus.
واحدة من هذه المناطق تسمى التَّلْفيفُ الجَبْهِيُّ السفلي الأيسر.
So if someone said, "My likelihood of suffering from cancer is 50 percent,"
فإذا قال أحدٌ "إمكانية إصابتي بالسرطان هي 50%"،
and we said, "Hey, good news.
و قلنا "إسمع! خبر سار.
Average likelihood is 30 percent,"
متوسط الإمكانية هو 30%".
the left inferior frontal gyrus would respond fiercely.
سيستجيب التلفيف الجبهي السفلي الأيسر بشراسة.
And it didn't matter if you're an extreme optimist, a mild optimist
و لا فرق إن كنت متفائلا متطرفا أو معتدلا
or slightly pessimistic,
أو متشائما قليلا
everyone's left inferior frontal gyrus
فالتلفيف الجبهي السفلي الأيسر لكلٍّ منهم
was functioning perfectly well,
يعمل بشكل جيد تمامًا،
whether you're Barack Obama or Woody Allen.
سواءًا أكنت باراك أوباما أو وودي ألن.
On the other side of the brain,
في الجهة الأخرى من الدماغ،
the right inferior frontal gyrus was responding to bad news.
كان التلفيف الجبهي السفلي الأيمن يستجيب للأخبارالسيئة.
And here's the thing: it wasn't doing a very good job.
و هنا تكمن المسألة: لم يكن يؤدي مهمته على وجة جيّد.
The more optimistic you were,
كلّما كنت أكثر تفاؤلاً،
the less likely this region was
كلما قلّ احتمال أن تقوم هذه المنطقة
to respond to unexpected negative information.
بالاستجابة للأخبار السلبية غير المنتظرة.
And if your brain is failing
و إن تعطّل عمل الدماغ
at integrating bad news about the future,
عن التقاط الأخبار السيئة المتعلقة بالمستقبل،
you will constantly leave your rose-tinted spectacles on.
ستدع مَشاهِدَكَ الوردية تخطر عليك بانتظام.
So we wanted to know, could we change this?
فأردنا معرفة هل بإمكاننا تغيير هذا؟
Could we alter people's optimism bias
هل يمكننا أن نحوّرميل الناس للتفاؤل
by interfering with the brain activity in these regions?
بالتدخل في النشاط الدماغي في هذه المناطق؟
And there's a way for us to do that.
وهناك وسيلة تسمح لنا بفعل ذلك.
This is my collaborator Ryota Kanai.
هذا أحد العاملين في مخبرنا روياتا كانايي
And what he's doing is he's passing a small magnetic pulse
وما يفعله هو تمرير نبضٍ مغناطيسيّ
through the skull of the participant in our study
عبر جمجمة المشاركين في دراستنا
into their inferior frontal gyrus.
نحو تلفيفهم الجبهي السفلي.
And by doing that,
وبهذا،
he's interfering with the activity of this brain region
فهو يتّدخل في نشاط هذه المنطقة من الدماغ
for about half an hour.
لمدة نصف الساعة تقريبا.
After that everything goes back to normal, I assure you.
أُطمئنكم أنّ كلّ شيء يرجع إلى وضعه العادي بعدها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So let's see what happens.
فلننظر ماذا يحدث.
First of all, I'm going to show you
بدايةً، سوف أريكم
the average amount of bias that we see.
معدل مقدار الميل الذي نلاحظه
So if I was to test all of you now,
فلو أني قمت الآن باختباركم جميعاً،
this is the amount that you would learn
هذا هو مقدارما قد تتعلمونه
more from good news relative to bad news.
بشكلٍ أكبر من الأخبار السارة مقارنةً بالأخبار السيئة.
Now we interfere with the region
و الآن نتدّخل في المنطقة
that we found to integrate negative information in this task,
التي وجدنا بأنها تلتقط الأخبار السيئة في هذه المَهمة،
and the optimism bias grew even larger.
فارتفع مقدار الميل للتفاؤل أكثر.
We made people more biased in the way that they process information.
لقد جعلنا الناس أكثر ميلا في أسلوب معالجتهم للمعلومات.
Then we interfered with the brain region
ثمّ تدخلنا في المنطقة
that we found to integrate good news in this task,
التي وجدنا بأنها تلتقط الأخبار الجيدة في هذه المَهمة،
and the optimism bias disappeared.
فاختفى الميل للتفاؤل.
We were quite amazed by these results
لقد دُهشنا تماماً لهذه النتائج
because we were able to eliminate
لأنّنا تمكنّا من إقصاء
a deep-rooted bias in humans.
ميلٍ إنسانيّ متجذّرٍ.
And at this point we stopped and we asked ourselves,
وها هنا توقّفنا لنسأل أنفسنا،
would we want to shatter the optimism illusion into tiny little bits?
أنرغب في تحطيم وهم التفاؤل قِطعاً قِطعاً؟
If we could do that, would we want to take people's optimism bias away?
إن أمكننا ذلك، أنرغب في انتزاع ميل الناس للتفاؤل؟
Well I've already told you about all of the benefits of the optimism bias,
حسناً لقد سبق وأن ذكرت لكم كل مزايا الميل للتفاؤل،
which probably makes you want to hold onto it for dear life.
والتي قد تجعلكم تتشبثون به،
But there are, of course, pitfalls,
لكن توجد له عيوبٌ
and it would be really foolish of us to ignore them.
لا نتجاهلها إلاّ سفهاً.
Take for example this email I recieved
فلنأخذ على سبيل المثال هذه الرسالة الإلكترونية التي تلقيتها
from a firefighter here in California.
من رجل إطفاءٍ هنا بكالفورنيا.
He says, "Fatality investigations for firefighters
يقول: "في التحقيقات حول حالات وفاة رجال الإطفاء
often include 'We didn't think the fire was going to do that,'
غالباً ما نسمع أقوالاً مثل "لم نكن نتوقع بأن تفعل النار ذلك"،
even when all of the available information
حتى و لو كانت كل المعلومات المتوفرة
was there to make safe decisions."
قد تسمح باتخاذ قرارات آمنة".
This captain is going to use our findings on the optimism bias
سيستعمل هذا الكابتن اكتشافنا حول الميل للتفاؤل
to try to explain to the firefighters
ليحاول أن يشرح لرجال الإطفاء
why they think the way they do,
لماذا يفكّرون بالطريقة التي يفكّرون بها،
to make them acutely aware of this very optimistic bias in humans.
لتوعيتهم من غير لبسٍ بهذا الميل للتفاؤل الشديد في الإنسان.
So unrealistic optimism can lead to risky behavior,
فالتفاؤل غير الواقعي قد يؤدي إلى سلوك متهور،
to financial collapse, to faulty planning.
إلى إفلاسٍ ماليّ، إلى تخطيطٍ خاطئ.
The British government, for example,
الحكومة البريطانية، على سبيل المثال،
has acknowledged that the optimism bias
اعترفت بأنّ الميل للتفاؤل
can make individuals more likely
قد يجعل الأفراد أكثرعرضةً
to underestimate the costs and durations of projects.
لتقييم تكاليف و مدة المشاريع بصفة أدنى مما تتطلب.
So they have adjusted the 2012 Olympic budget
فقد قاموا بتعديل ميزانية الألعاب الأولمبية 2012
for the optimism bias.
باعتبار الميل للتفاؤل.
My friend who's getting married in a few weeks
صديقي المقبل على الزواج في غضون بضعة أسابيع
has done the same for his wedding budget.
قام بنفس الشيء بالنسبة لميزانية زفافه.
And by the way, when I asked him about his own likelihood of divorce,
وعلى سبيل الذكر، لمّا سألته عن إمكانية طلاقه شخصيّا،
he said he was quite sure it was zero percent.
قال أنه متأكدٌ تماما بأنها صفر بالمائة.
So what we would really like to do,
فما نريد فعله حقيقةً،
is we would like to protect ourselves from the dangers of optimism,
هو أن نحمي أنفسنا من مخاطر التفاؤل،
but at the same time remain hopeful,
لكن، في نفس الوقت نبقى متفائلين،
benefiting from the many fruits of optimism.
فنستفيد بذلك من ثمرات التفاؤل العديدة.
And I believe there's a way for us to do that.
و أعتقد أن هناك أسلوبا يمكّننا من فعل ذلك.
The key here really is knowledge.
المفتاح هنا هو المعرفة.
We're not born with an innate understanding of our biases.
نحن لم نولد بفهمٍ فطريّ لميولاتنا.
These have to be identified by scientific investigation.
إنها تحتاج إلى أبحاثٍ علمية تبيّنها لنا.
But the good news is that becoming aware of the optimism bias
لكن البشرى هي أن اكتساب الوعي بالميل للتفاؤل
does not shatter the illusion.
لا يحطّم الوهم.
It's like visual illusions,
إنه كالأوهام البصرية،
in which understanding them does not make them go away.
حيث أنّ فهمها لا يزيلها.
And this is good because it means
و هذا جيّد لأنه يعني
we should be able to strike a balance,
أنّنا يجب أن نتوصّل إلى توازنٍ
to come up with plans and rules
لكي نوجِد مخططات و قواعدًا
to protect ourselves from unrealistic optimism,
نحمي بها أنفسنا من التفاول غير الواقعي،
but at the same time remain hopeful.
لكن نُبقي على آمالنا في نفس الوقت.
I think this cartoon portrays it nicely.
أعتقد أنّ هذا الكاريكاتير يصوّر المسألة بلطافة.
Because if you're one of these pessimistic penguins up there
لأنّك لو كنت أحد تلك البطاريق المتشائمة
who just does not believe they can fly,
الذي لا يكاد يصدّق أنها لا تطير،
you certainly never will.
فبالتأكيد لن تستطيع ذلك أبدًا.
Because to make any kind of progress,
لأنّه من أجل التقدم بأي شكلٍ من الأشكال،
we need to be able to imagine a different reality,
نحتاج أن نكون قادرين على تصوّر واقع مغاير،
and then we need to believe that that reality is possible.
و حينها نحتاج أن نؤمن بأن ذلك الواقع ممكن.
But if you are an extreme optimistic penguin
لكن لو كنت بطريقاً شديد التفاؤل
who just jumps down blindly hoping for the best,
يقفز فقط وعيناه مغمضتان على أمل الأفضل،
you might find yourself in a bit of a mess when you hit the ground.
فقد تجد نفسك في ورطة عندما تصطدم بالأرض.
But if you're an optimistic penguin
لكن لو كنت بطريقًا متفائلاً
who believes they can fly,
يعتقد أنّ بإمكانه أن يطير،
but then adjusts a parachute to your back
لكنك تصطحب مظلّةً على ظهرك
just in case things don't work out exactly as you had planned,
احتياطاً في حالة إذا ما سارت الأمور على خلاف ما خطّطته،
you will soar like an eagle,
فسترتفع عاليّاً كالصقر،
even if you're just a penguin.
حتى و إن كنت مجرّد بطريقً
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)